So today's דף Daf is י"ח Yud Ches and we pick up
at the very top of it, you know just for context let's
just read from two lines from the bottom of י"ז עמוד ב'.
Yud Zayin Amud Bet. We had just read the משנה Mishna of
בית הלל Beit Hillel and בית שמאי Beit Shammai about what can
you take to the מקוה Mikvah on שבת Shabbos where or שבת
Shabbos or יום טוב Yom Tov where everybody agrees you can't immerse
vessels, כלים, Kelim, but there's a debate whether a person can immerse.
So the גמרא Gemara says דכולי עלמא מיהת D'chulei Alma mi-hat two
lines from the bottom on י"ז עמוד ב', Yud Zayin Amud Bet,
דכולי עלמא מיהת D'chulei Alma mi-hat everybody agrees nevertheless, כלי בשבת לא
Kli be-Shabbos lo that you can't immerse a vessel on שבת. Shabbos.
מאי טעמא Mai Ta'ama what's the reason? So אמר רבא Amar Rava
says רבא, Rava, גזירה שמא יטלנו בידו ויעבירנו ארבע אמות ברשות הרבים.
Gzeira shema yitlenu be-yado ve-yavirenu arba amot bi-reshut harabbim.
We're afraid that if we let you take a vessel to the
מקוה Mikvah on שבת Shabbos that you'll carry it, you know you'll
start bringing your vessels to the מקוה Mikvah so it'll lead to
carrying. As we pointed out it's the exact same language that רבא
Rava uses in the explanation of why you can't take a לולב
Lulav on שבת Shabbos and pointed out an interesting question about whether
it's clear that he initially said this statement in both cases or
it's possible he said it in one and then the גמרא Gemara
applied it to the other. But this is the explanation he gives
here. So אמר ליה אביי Amar lei Abaye so אביי Abaye said
to him, יש לו בור בחצרו מאי Yesh lo bor be-chatzeiro mai
so why should there be a problem if you've got a well
which is essentially a מקוה Mikvah
in your חצר chatzer in your yard and classically people, you know,
would have walls around their courtyards with multiple houses that's the whole
point of עירובי חצרות. Eruvei Chatzerot. So why should that be a
problem? And presumably that was not such an uncommon thing because where
else would people be getting their water from? So he said, איכא
למימר מאי איכא למימר Ika le-meimar mai ika le-meimar what can you
say? אמר ליה גזירה בור בחצרו אטו בור ברשות הרבים. Amar lei
Gzeira bor be-chatzeiro atu bor bi-reshut harabbim. Alright, it's a גזירה, Gzeira,
you know, we don't allow it even if it's the well is
in your yard, is in your courtyard because it'll lead to cases
where the only available well is in the public domain and it'll
lead to carrying. So the גמרא Gemara says התינח שבת, Ha-tenach Shabbos,
okay fine I understand why it should be forbidden on שבת. Shabbos.
But יום טוב מאי איכא למימר, Yom Tov mai ika le-meimar, יום
טוב Yom Tov carrying is allowed, so why shouldn't we allow it
on יום טוב? Yom Tov? So the גמרא Gemara says גזרו יום
טוב אטו
שבת. Gazu Yom Tov atu Shabbos. Alright they forbade יום טוב Yom
Tov because it'll lead to cases on שבת. Shabbos. Now again that's
a little bit funny because you know there's so many things now
we should now forbid on יום טוב Yom Tov because it'll lead
to שבת Shabbos that are things that are fundamentally not concerns about
יום טוב. Yom Tov. Right, אוכל נפש, Ochel Nefesh, right everything related
to אוכל נפש, Ochel Nefesh, you know like reading
לאור הנר, Le'or haner, a million types of גזירות Gzeiras you get
by שבת Shabbos that aren't relevant because the מלאכות Melachot are not
those מלאכות Melachot are not problematic on יום טוב. Yom Tov. One
interesting in particular that we do say of this you should be
aware of though is the גזירת מרחצאות Gzeirat Merchatza'ot which is the
bathing in heated water, that there the concern is if we let
people bathe in heated water even heated from before שבת Shabbos that
the רבנן Rabbanan was not allowed to do it because you'll come
to heat up the water, they'll go to these bathhouses you know
the Roman bathhouses, and they'll go ahead and they'll heat up the
water on שבת. Shabbos. Now there's no reason that should really be
a problem on יום טוב, Yom Tov, but nevertheless it's forbidden. Now
interestingly you should say well you know is it really שוה לכל
נפש, shaveh le-chol nefesh, etc. so there's a whole interesting question about
that about taking the hot shower a hot shower on יום טוב.
Yom Tov. Is it considered something that you know in it used
to be bathing you know hot water was only something that everybody
needed for their hands and face and feet not for their whole
body. At least whatever we'll see that later, but nowadays a number
of פוסקים Poskim say and I פסקן pasken this way as well
that you could take a hot shower on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
You have to be careful not to like squeeze out your hair,
use liquid soap not bar soap, but take a hot shower on
יום טוב. Yom Tov. But you still can't take a hot bath
because of the גזירת מרחצאות Gzeirat Merchatza'ot even though that's not really
so relevant on יום טוב. Yom Tov. So every now and then
we do find a גזירה Gzeira that was started in שבת Shabbos
and applied to יום טוב Yom Tov although fundamentally there really shouldn't
be that problem by יום טוב. Yom Tov. So that's what he's
saying here. Yes it doesn't make sense by יום טוב Yom Tov
but that's what we do we forbid יום טוב Yom Tov as
well not to dunk vessels because it'll lead to carrying on שבת.
Shabbos. So the גמרא Gemara says ומי גזרינן U-mi gazrinan do we
really make such a גזירה? Gzeira? והתנן, Ve-ha-tenan,
meaning not just make a גזירה Gzeira but do we really make
the way you framed it there's a lot of גזירה לגזירה Gzeira
le-Gzeira going on here, right it starts by one שבת Shabbos case
of a בור ברשות הרבים bor bi-reshut harabbim and then we outlaw
a lot of other related things. So there's a lot of גזירה
לגזירה. Gzeira le-Gzeira. So is that really are we really that concerned?
והתנן Ve-ha-tenan we taught in the משנה Mishna ושוין שמשיקין את המים
ve-shavin she-mashkin et ha-mayim שמשיקין את המים, she-mashikin et ha-mayim, excuse me,
you do השקה hashaka to the water בכלי אבן לטהרן bi-kli even
le-taharan אבל לא מטבילין. aval lo matbilin. So you can do השקה
hashaka with water to purify the water, you put it in the
מקוה Mikvah and it connects to the water of the מקוה, Mikvah,
but you cannot with a stone vessel but you can't use an
impure vessel and intend to purify the impure vessel in the process.
Okay, ואי איתא, Ve-i ita, if what you're saying is correct that
there's a lot of גזירה לגזירה gezeira li'gezeiras going on here, so
נגזר השקה אטו הטבלה. nigzar hashaka atu hatvala. So how do we
allow this thing with the water? We should forbid it because it'll
easily lead to the case of dunking the כלי kli itself. So
the גמרא Gemara says, ותסברא, vitispra, does that make sense that we
should make that גזירה? gezeira? אי אית ליה מים יפים
הני למה לי למהוי להו השקה. i islei mayin yafim hani lama
li lemeihavei lehu hashaka. If you have other good water to use
that's טהור, tahor, why would you bother doing השקה hashaka with this
water? אלא ella why go to all this effort, it's just water,
you know, spill it out use your good water. אלא דלית ליה,
ella deleislei, it must be the only reason you're bothering is because
you don't have any other water to use. וכיון דלית ליה, ve'keivan
de'leislei, since you don't have any other water to use, מזדהר בהו,
mizhazhar behu, you'll be careful not to carry. Now what does that
mean? Okay, so you don't have any other water to use. Why
does that mean you won't accidentally carry it? So רש"י Rashi basically
says, and this is going to be the same thing רש"י Rashi
is going to say in the next few answers of the גמרא,
Gemara, that what it just means is it's a מילתא דלא שכיחא.
milsa de'lo sh'chiach. That this is an uncommon scenario, and since it's
an uncommon scenario, even if we make גזירה לגזירה, gezeira li'gezeiras, we
make גזירה לגזירה gezeira li'gezeiras in sort of the standard cases. But
in even though what might be uncommon is that A will lead
to B, but the circumstances of the case themselves, of the initial
case, is common. You need to take a thing to the מקוה
mikva on יום טוב. Yom Tov. And they, you know, that's common.
So or the fact, you know, so the fact that it might
lead to a case of from doing it from יום טוב Yom
Tov to doing it on שבת, Shabbos, that might be not so
common, but the initial circumstances is common as opposed to here, the
initial circumstances of needing to do השקה hashaka with your water is
very uncommon circumstance and the principle is מילתא דלא שכיחא לא גזרו
רבנן. milsa de'lo sh'chiach lo gazru rabanan. They didn't make a גזירה
gezeira for cases where the initial circumstances of the case were לא
שכיחא lo sh'chiach as opposed to what we're talking about which is
we might be making גזירה לגזירה gezeira li'gezeiras but the initial circumstances
are שכיח. sh'chiach. Okay, now
so
now,
question though is, is that fine, that explains why the גמרא Gemara
says why don't we, why aren't we afraid that if we let
you bring it to the מקוה mikva the water, you'll come to
carry the כלי. kli. But there's a simpler question, which is why
don't we say if we let you take the water to the
מקוה, mikva, you'll come to carry the not the כלי, kli, but
the water? Right, so that's what תוספות Tosfos says. If you look
at תוספות, Tosfos, he says ונגזר השקה אטו הטבלה. ve'nigzar hashaka atu
hatvala. So says וקשיא לפרוך נגזר משום שמא יעבירנו ארבע אמות ברשות
הרבים השקה. ve'kashya lifroch nigzar mishum shema ya'avireinu arba amos bi'reshus harabbim
hashaka. Forget the כלי, kli, you know, let's be afraid that you'll
come to carry the water. בשלמא גבי הטבלת כלי צריך למיגזר שמא
יעבירנו לפי שבהול להטבילו, bishlama gabbei hatvalas kli tzarich linigzar shema ya'avireinu
lefi shelohu lehatvilo, you're very like pressured, אבל בהשקת
מים אין בהול כל כך להשיקן דאפשר במים אחרים. aval behashakas mayim
ein lohu kol kach lehashikan de'efshar be'mayim acherim. So basically what he's
saying until the גמרא Gemara introduced presumably the point that you have
no other water, where if we're assuming that you have other water,
so we're not so concerned that you know, like you're so, this
is so urgent. But somehow with vessels maybe you'd only have a
much more limited supply of vessels. Not exactly clear why exactly what
that answer is.
Yes, you spent five seconds describing what this is. Would you carry
water without a כלי? kli? Yeah, carrying water with a כלי?
kli?
Yeah, I don't know, doing it in your hands? Yeah, I don't
know, but so you're right, I mean what?
You're carrying in something that's not מקבל טומאה? mekabel tumah?
Yes,
but you're carrying that other thing as well. Right. But the גמרא,
Gemara, but I don't think he means carrying it with your hands.
He means why does the גמרא Gemara say let's not allow the
water because it'll lead to a case of a vessel? If the
very case of the water itself is a case of carrying if
you leave your חצר chatzer because of the water, because of the
vessel that the water's in, but not because it'll lead to a
different case which is only about a vessel. Okay, just saying why
are we concerned, why does the גמרא Gemara frame it, how do
we allow the water maybe it'll lead to a case of a
vessel? It says how do we allow the water, you'll step out
of your חצר chatzer and it'll be carrying? That's what the גמרא
Gemara should have asked. Okay, wait five seconds on השקה. hashaka.
Well, all that is is again what that normally you cannot be
מטהר metaher food. They only allowed it by water and presumably the
reason, the logic somehow being that when you connect, when you put
the water in the מקוה mikva it's not like you're immersing water,
it becomes but it becomes part of the מקוה. mikva. Once it
becomes part of the מקוה mikva and then it's taken out again,
it's like it's something completely new, so it's not a process of
טהרה. tahara. That seems to be the logic. Okay, so now the
גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay, so we have this idea of
גזירה לגזירה. gezeira li'gezeira. How about the case of the water? Why
does that not fall under the גזירה? gezeira? And the answer is
לא שכיחא. lo sh'chiach. Okay, so גמרא Gemara says איתיבי eisei I'll
ask you on this. מדלין בדלי טמא והוא טהור. madlin bi'dli tamei
ve'hu tahor. You can draw water with an impure כלי kli and
whoops, look at that, the כלי kli becomes טהור tahor in the
process. Okay, now why is that different than when you do השקה
hashaka you cannot use an impure כלי? kli? So רש"י Rashi says
because in this case basically you don't start with you know in
that
case... Being מטהר mitaher something. You're being מטהר mitaher the water. So
if we let you do it with an impure vessel, that'll be
defined as being טובל הכלי. tovel hakli. That's why that's a problem.
Whereas here, fundamentally the act you're doing is drawing water, right? That's
what fundamentally you're doing. You're not taking something to a מקוה. mikvah.
You're drawing water from the well. So since that's fundamentally what you're
doing, even if you use a טמא tamei vessel, it's not clearly
an act of טבילת כלי, tevilas kli, and therefore it's allowed. So
the גמרא Gemara says okay, that's all very nice in terms of
framing it in a certain way, in a formal way, it's not
as much of an act of טבילה, tevila, but why aren't we
concerned אטו דליי דחקלאי? atu dalyai dechaklai? If we have so many
concerns of carrying? So the גמרא Gemara says ואי סברא נגזור דילמא
אתו לאטבולי בעיניה. ve-ee savra nigzor dilma atu l'itvulei be-einei. If it's
true that we make all of these גזירה לגזירה, gezeira l'gezeira, let's
say you can't do the drawing of water because that'll lead to
an intentional טבילה. tevila. So the גמרא Gemara says no, שאני התם
shani hosam or just say, or maybe say just using
the bucket will come to carrying the bucket. גמרא Gemara says no,
שאני התם מתוך שלא הותר לו אלא על ידי דליו דליו זכור
הוא. shani hosam mitoch shelo hutar lo ela al yedei dalyo dalyo
zachur hu. Therefore basically it's the same answer. There because we're only
allowing you to do it through your bucket, basically we're only framing
it as a drawing of water, not a טבילה, tevila, you'll remember
and it won't come to a case of doing טבילה. tevila. Obviously
they couldn't say to people don't draw water from your well with
a bucket on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov. I mean,
they made all these special תקנות takanos to make it possible to
draw water from the well, the whole פסי ביראות pasi biraos and
so on. So fundamentally that's a category that's allowed on שבת Shabbos
and יום טוב. Yom Tov. But the גמרא Gemara is saying but
if it's טמא tamei and so on, why don't we make a
גזירה? gezeira? And says no, because fundamentally it's staying within that category
of drawing water and therefore it's not in the גזירה לגזירה gezeira
l'gezeira type of a thing, which means that even with the גזירה
לגזירה, gezeira l'gezeira, and this is the same as the idea about
the השקה hashaka of the water, it doesn't mean in a way
it's almost like
not even against the סברא, svara, it's actually very consistent. גזירה לגזירה,
gezeira l'gezeira, what allows us to make a safeguard to a safeguard
to a safeguard to a safeguard? So the גמרא Gemara is saying
well then let's אסור assur everything, and then it gives like formalistic
answers. This isn't really a טבילה, tevila, it's more like drawing water.
This isn't really a טבילה, tevila, it's more השקה. hashaka. So say
well, that's not a fair answer, that's a formalistic answer and you're
saying we have all of these real concerns. But in a way
it's an answer that makes a lot of sense, because what legitimates
גזירה לגזירה לגזירה gezeira l'gezeira l'gezeira and a million concerns built on
one another? And the answer primarily is that of גזירה לגזירה gezeira
l'gezeira is that it's not that we really are always concerned that
A will lead to B will lead to C. It's a formalistic
point. If we're going to forbid something, we're going to forbid that
case like across the board. We're going to say don't do טבילה
tevila for שבת, Shabbos, don't do on יום טוב, Yom Tov, not
necessarily because we're really concerned that A will lead to B will
lead to C. But in a formal way, when we forbid a
category, we forbid everything that falls in that category. If that's true,
then in the same formalistic way we can say if it's not
defined as טבילה, tevila, if it's defined as השקה hashaka or it's
not an act of טבילה tevila but it's an act of drawing
water, then it's outside of those formalistic boundaries. So that's basically what
the גמרא Gemara is saying. It starts by saying oh, if you're
so concerned and making a million גזירות, gezeiras, forbid this too. It
says yeah, but that's not formally the same act. Yes.
So he draws the water in the bucket from the well. Yeah.
What's he do with that water?
Leave it there. What do you mean?
Right, in other words he's not... Right, so where does the מקוה
mikvah exactly come in?
It would be if it's a יום טוב, Yom Tov, it could
be anywhere, and if it's שבת, Shabbos, it's in the חצר. chatzer.
But the point is, it's the exact same scenario. You're going to
a well with a כלי, kli, but the reality is that they
never, but certainly by יום טוב Yom Tov it's not a problem
unless you put it under a heading of טבילה tevila which is
אסור. assur. And by שבת, Shabbos, they actually made it
easier for you to draw water on שבת Shabbos because it's such
a necessity. So that's the whole point, that this is a category
that we allow on שבת, Shabbos, but if it's defined as טבילה,
tevila, we don't allow it. But the גמרא Gemara is saying who
cares what it's defined as, why aren't we concerned that it'll lead
to the other case?
Right, so in other words he needs the water in the house
for whatever it is. Yeah.
Like turning on your faucet.
Right. Otherwise he would have taken water from the מקוה mikvah in
order to do it to his house?
No, what do you mean otherwise? He would have used a טהור
tahor כלי. kli. By using a טמא tamei כלי, kli, what you're
doing is you're sneaking through the back door an act of טבילה.
tevila. Right.
Right. So in other words, they used a מקוה mikvah also as
a source of cooking water or...
The מקוה mikvah was their well. You
have this in like in Europe, the מקואות mikvahs are these basically
just like deep wells is what they basically are. Imagine what the
real מסירות נפש mesirus nefesh was to go down there and boy,
it was very deep and dangerous and so on. It's interesting to
note because sometimes there's a discussion of מים חיים, mayim chayim, the
גמרא Gemara says, the גמרא Gemara is It’s never clear. It’s actually
quite fascinating. The תורה Torah says a זב zav needs מים חיים.
mayim chayim. It never says by a זבה zava whether she does
or does not. And some of the גאונים Geonim said that a
זבה zava also needs מים חיים. mayim chayim. The problem is that
according to the גמרא נידה, Gemara Niddah, we treat nowadays, you know,
all women as a ספק זבה, safek zava, which would require מים
חיים. mayim chayim. Now when מים חיים mayim chayim I think about
it, I think like about a, you know, I don’t know, a
bubbling brook or something, some type of fresh spring. But so how
could they have demanded that? But the reality is that a well
is מים חיים mayim chayim because you’re digging straight down, it’s not
rainwater that’s collected, it’s water from underground. And if most of their
מקוואות mikvaos were wells, then it wasn’t a big חידוש chiddush to
say, okay, you need מים חיים, mayim chayim, that’s what we do
anyway. But thankfully, that position was completely rejected by the ראשונים Rishonim
or else we couldn’t do any of our מקוואות mikvaos nowadays. You
know, but anyway, but the reality is that yes, the מקווה mikvah
often would be a well, the same type of thing you would
get water from. Yes.
Just getting back to this then, how do we distinguish between taking
a bath, taking a shower, which was all גזירת מרחץ? gezeirat merchatzah?
I’m not answering that. We’ll get to it. I shouldn’t have brought
it in. I knew you’d get this done. We’ll get to it
when we get back. But the difference is one is immersion in
a body of water and the other is having water spilled on
top of you, yes.
We found a מקווה mikvah in Montreal that is מים חיים. mayim
chayim.
Oh yeah? Is it a well?
It’s a spring.
It’s a spring. Okay. So now the גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, so that’s the basic question. Why didn’t we make these גזירות?
gezeiros? And the גמרא Gemara says, no, these cases in a formalistic
way are different. It’s taking, it’s drawing water with a bucket, it’s
not going to the מקווה. mikvah. איתיביה Eisivei asked you: כלי שנטמא
ערב יום טוב אין מטבילין אותו ביום טוב. Kli shenitameh erev Yom
Tov ein matbilin oso be-Yom Tov. If
a vessel got טמא tamei ערב יום טוב, erev Yom Tov, we
don’t let you do it on יום טוב Yom Tov because you
should have taken care of it from beforehand. ביום טוב מטבילין אותו
ביום טוב. Be-Yom Tov matbilin oso be-Yom Tov. So this is a
new twist that we hadn’t seen, which is a nice leniency. If
it got טמא tamei on יום טוב, Yom Tov, then we allow
you because then you got, you’re stuck and you know, you didn’t
have a choice. What do you mean? Well, that’s a good point.
ואי איתא, Ve-im issa, if it’s true that you have all these
גזירות, gezeiros, נגזר דיום טוב אטו ערב יום טוב. nigzar de-Yom Tov
atu erev Yom Tov. So you know, to make these types of
distinctions, you have a case to do it, not a case to
do it, that shows that we’re sort of making, you know, making
the prohibition with very fine distinctions. Your whole approach is we אוסר
oser it across the board. So if it’s across the board, we
shouldn’t allow it even if it got טמא tamei on יום טוב
Yom Tov as well. So the גמרא Gemara says: טומאה ביום טוב
מילתא דלא שכיחא, מילתא דלא שכיחא לא גזרו בה רבנן. Tumah be-Yom
Tov milsa d’lo sh’chicha, milsa d’lo sh'chicha lo gazru bah rabanan. Similar
to what רש"י Rashi said, the earlier answer, the way רש"י Rashi
explained it: Things getting טומאה tumah on יום טוב Yom Tov is
an uncommon scenario. Why? Because everybody’s already טהור, tahor, everybody wants to
be טהור tahor on the רגל regel because עליה לרגל aliya l’regel
and so on. And therefore, this is such a rare exception that
it did not fall under... it’s not because the concern wasn’t there,
okay, but even sometimes just we don’t, the גזירות gezeiros do not
apply to rare exceptional cases. איתיביה, Eisivei, says okay, I’ll ask you
again: כלי שנטמא באב טומאה אין מטבילין אותו ביום טוב, בולד הטומאה
מטבילין אותו ביום טוב. Kli shenitameh be-ava tumah ein matbilin oso be-Yom
Tov, be-vlada tumah matbilin oso be-Yom Tov. If a vessel became טמא
tamei with an אב טומאה, ava tumah, which then the vessel is
a ראשון, rishon, then you cannot be מטביל matbil it on יום
טוב. Yom Tov. If it became טמא tamei with a ולד הטומאה,
vlada tumah, which means a... it touched something that was a ראשון,
rishon, that already was a derivative, then the vessel would be a
שני. sheni. Now the reality is that vessels don’t become שני, sheni,
only foods become שני. sheni. However, for as we’re going to see,
for certain תרומה terumah purposes, it might be considered... it could be
considered a שני. sheni. So therefore, in that type of a case,
you can be מטביל matbil it on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
What, if it became טמא tamei on יום טוב Yom Tov or?
Well, oh, so that’s a good question. So רש"י Rashi says is
even if it became טמא tamei on ערב יום טוב. erev Yom
Tov. It’s an additional leniency. If it became טמא tamei on יום
טוב, Yom Tov, even with an אב טומאה ava tumah you could
do it. If it became טמא tamei on ערב יום טוב, erev
Yom Tov, then even there you can do it if it was
only with a ולד הטומאה. vlada tumah. Okay, and the basic logic
is that it’s not considered, you know, it’s not considered
a real טומאה tumah as much. Okay, so it’s not so טמא.
tamei. So it’s only טמא tamei from a תרומה terumah perspective and
only rabbinically. So then we would let you do it. It’s a...
so again, it’s a very nice leniency here, it doesn’t fit into
this category of an across-the-board categorical גזירה. gezeirah. So the גמרא Gemara
says: ואי איתא, Ve-im issa, if what you’re saying is correct that
we make these broad גזירות, gezeiros, נגזר הא אטו הא. nigzar ha
atu ha. So let’s be concerned that a ולד הטומאה vlada tumah
allowing it will lead to an אב טומאה. ava tumah. Now again,
it’s a funny question because you could say: נגזור, Nigzor, that in
a case of ולד הטומאה vlada tumah you’ll come to carry it,
right? Who cares that it’ll lead to an אב טומאה ava tumah
case? Let’s make a גזירה gezeirah you’ll come to carry it. So
תוספות Tosafot sort of deals with that. But anyway, let’s take a
look at the גמרא. Gemara. So the גמרא Gemara says: ולד הטומאה
היכי משכחת לן? Vlada tumah heichi mishkachat lan? No, where do you
have a case of ולד הטומאה vlada tumah being a problem? גבי
כהנים. Gabi kohanim. It’s only by כהנים, kohanim, because then the כלי
kli that’s a שני sheni will make תרומה terumah into a שלישי.
shlishi. So the whole thing is a כהנים kohanim case. כהנים זריזין
הם, Kohanim rizmei, כהנים kohanim are careful, so we’re not so concerned.
They’re the ones that are going to want to be... put it
in the מקווה, mikvah, they’re going to be extra careful. Okay. So
now the גמרא Gemara says: תא שמע, Ta shema, come and hear:
דאמר רבי חייא בר אשי אמר רב, D’amar Rebbe Chiya bar Ashi
amar Rav, נידה שאין לה בגדים, niddah she-ein lah begadim, a woman
who
is a נידה niddah who doesn’t have any clothes... clothes that are
טהור, tahor, she only has the clothes that she's been wearing as
a נידה niddah that are טמא, tamei, so she can go to
the מקווה mikvah on שבת Shabbos or יום טוב Yom Tov as
we just learned, but how is she going to get טהור tahor
clothes to wear? So what will she do? So מערמת וטובלת בבגדיה.
me'aremet v'tovelet bevagdeha. She can go to the מקווה mikvah with her
clothes on, okay? And if the clothes are loose fitting enough, it
won't be a חציצה. chatzitzah. So the גמרא Gemara says, ואי איתא,
v'ei ita, but if what you're saying is correct, נגזר דילמא אתי
לאטבולי במאני. nigzar dilma ati l'atbuli b'manei. Let's be concerned that if
we're going to make גזירה לגזירה, gezeira l'gezeira, that you'll come to
if you wrap people to טבול tovel with their clothes on, they'll
come to be טובל tovel their clothes when they're not on their
body. The גמרא Gemara says no, שאני התם מתוך שהותרה לה על
ידי מלבוש זכורה היא. shani hatam mitoch she'hutrah lah al yedei malbush
zchurah hi. Same answer. That's a very exceptional case. She'll remember because
she's only doing it while she's wearing the clothes. That's quite something
that she's not going to easily forget and mix up. And therefore
now again, that answer could be the answer that's like the answer
with the bucket, which is a formalistic difference,
which says that
is not, you know, a being טובל tovel clothes. That's being טובל
tovel yourself with your clothes on. It's a little different than
the bucket.
The bucket we wouldn't say is an act of טבילה tevilah at
all.
It's completely incidental. The bucket becomes טהור, tahor, but it's an act
of drawing water. Here, it is an act of טבילה tevilah of
her, but it's not an act of טבילה tevilah of the clothes.
It's a טבילה tevilah that she's doing with her clothes happening to
be on and that won't lead to being, that's categorically different than
an act of being טובל tovel the vessel. What did you want
to say, Dov? What? It's a very non-תלמודית Talmudit answer. Yes, the
right way to do it is to let somebody else טובל tovel
your clothes, put them in the dryer, then you go to the
מקווה. mikvah. Well, you can't do that because you can't be טובל
tovel vessels on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov. Right. The
whole point is not because she'll touch it when she's doing it.
Let her be טהור tahor and then let her do it herself.
The whole problem is that she doesn't have anything טהור tahor to
wear. Now, the other question is that, wait, you can soak your
clothes on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב? Yom Tov? So take a
look at תוספות. Tosafot. I mean, first of all, we'd say aren't
you afraid she'd squeeze them out? So before squeezing them out, isn't
the soaking itself an act of laundering? So look at תוספות, Tosafot,
מערמת וטובלת בבגדיה. me'aremet v'tovelet bevagdeha. תוספות Tosafot says תימה, teima, היינו
שרייה, hainu shriya, so you're immersing them in water. דשרייה אסור משום
מכבס ומלבן. d'shriya assur mishum mechabes u'melaben. דאמרינן שרייתו זו היא כיבוסו.
d'amrinan shriyato zu hi kibuso.
We say that immersing something in water is part of the act
of laundering it. Now, there's an interesting debate in the ראשונים Rishonim
how much in categorical terms to interpret that. That every act of
getting something wet, is it really שרייה shriya or is it only
under certain types of contexts which are the normal, which are the
normal, well, we're going to get to that, which is the normal
process of laundering. But תוספות Tosafot understands certainly getting something fully immersed
in water should be considered an act of laundering. ויש לומר v'yesh
lomar says תוספות, Tosafot, דהוא דהוי דרך טינוף שרי. d'hu de'havei derech
tinuf shari.
Since it's getting it dirty in the process, not clean. מקווה Mikvah
waters are presumably dirty and there's dirt on your body and so
on. That would, even though you're immersing it, it's not considered laundering.
ותימה דהיכא אנו מקנחים ידינו במפה בשבת? v'teima d'heicha anu mekunachim yadeinu
b'mapah b'Shabbos? How do we wipe our hands on a towel? הוי
שרייה ואסור משום מכבס ומלבן. havei shriya v'assur mishum mechabes u'melaben.
Now, of course you could say that's only slightly damp. That's not
immersing it in water. But you see here that תוספות Tosafot understands
that even slightly damp is a problem. אלא כיון דהוי דרך טינוף
שרי הכא נמי נימא הכי. ela kivan de'havei derech tinuf shari hacha
nami neima hachi. So here too, although there the whole point is
to get dirt off your hands on the towel, nevertheless here, the
waters aren't clean. Right. It makes it all dirty. Here, your body
isn't clean, the waters aren't clean, it's not a problem. But you
see by the way, and this becomes an issue, right? Some people
just, you know, they spill something on the tablecloth. They say, "Oh,
put on some seltzer" or they get a stain on their garment
and they put some water on it. So that's real מכבס. mechabes.
And again, not every ראשון Rishon says that just putting water on
a local spot is מכבס, mechabes, but certainly תוספות Tosafot feels that
way and his whole distinction here is whether it's דרך לכלוך derech
lichluch or not דרך לכלוך, derech lichluch, דרך טינוף. derech tinuf. Okay.
So yeah, you wanted to say something, Dov?
I did.
There's so many סוגיות sugyos that we've already seen about חציצה. chatzitzah.
Yeah. This is like a pretty glib... like it's not even treated.
Yeah. No. But there also are other examples about this, about wearing
clothes. Especially if they're loose fitting clothes. I mean, we have, you
know, if you think about people that wore flowing robes and their
underwear is really more like breeches, not tight fitting underwear, and it's
all pretty porous anyway. So yeah, I mean, you know, there are
גמרות Gemaros also though that you could be wearing clothes and it's
not a חציצה. chatzitzah. חציצה Chatzitzah is a tier closer to the
skin. You know. So yeah. But yeah, this is assumed that it
will not be a חציצה. chatzitzah.
I'm just curious, this in general, I mean, maybe somewhat uninformed, but
if you're talking about גזירה gezeira for גזירה, gezeira, I mean, we
still differentiate for instance between ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael and בבל. Bavel.
Like we'll still take תרומות terumot in בבל Bavel because גזירה gezeira
if you go to ארץ ישראל Eretz Yisrael then you won't be
taking תרומות ומעשרות. terumot u'ma'asrot. You know what I'm saying? Meaning like
we still draw the line in locations, right? So one more time?
What are you saying?
For instance...
Well, that's basically the same type of answer the גמרא Gemara is
given. That even when you say גזירה לגזירה, gezeira l'gezeira, which is
what I'm saying. גזירה לגזירה gezeira l'gezeira the way the גמרא Gemara
sort of saying is then we should just אסר assur everything. And
the גמרא's Gemara answer is no, even within the context of גזירה
לגזירה gezeira l'gezeira we can make formalistic distinctions. distinction. And what I'm
trying to say is that that's not an unfair answer; if anything
it makes complete sense, because גזירה לגזירה gezeirah legezeirah doesn't always really
mean, oh we're going to forbid every single case because we genuinely
believe that A will lead to B will lead to C. What
it means is we make something categorically forbidden, but categorically forbidden when
it falls into the formal definition. Something that falls outside the formal
definition is not part of that category. So that's most of these
answers work for that, like, you know, wearing clothes is different than
an act of טבילה tevilah of clothes. Drawing water is different than
an act of טבילה tevilah of water. It's not so good for
the answers of when it gets טמא tamei on יום טוב Yom
Tov as opposed to before יום טוב Yom Tov or ראשון לטומאה
rishon letumah as opposed to אב הטומאה. av hatumah. That's not really
a categorically different act. That's really just saying, yeah that's rare, so
we're going to let that go. Okay, which doesn't fit so much
within the same type of answer. But yes, we do make distinctions.
That's exactly what the גמרא Gemara is saying. Okay, so that's one
whole set of answers which explains what the גזירה gezeirah is and
somehow maneuvers its way through these different questions. Okay, so the גמרא
Gemara says like this.
Where were we? Ah, רב יוסף אמר גזירה משום סחיטה. Rav Yosef
amar gezeirah mishum sechitah.
Okay, which certainly seems to anyway have been the last case with
the clothes. We're afraid that if we let you dunk, if we
let you immerse, you'll come to squeeze things out. Now, not now,
that's fine if we're concerned about clothes, but a lot of כלים
keilim there's no סחיטה sechitah to be done. So the גמרא Gemara
says, but anyway it at least is applied on יום טוב Yom
Tov and not just on שבת. Shabbos.
So אמר ליה אביי, amar lei Abaye, so אביי Abaye said, תינח
כלים דבני סחיטה נינהו. teinach keilim devnei sechitah ninhu. That's good for
vessels that can be squeezed, like clothing. But כלים דלאו בני סחיטה
נינהו מאי איכא למימר? keilim delav bnei sechitah ninhu mai ika lemeimar?
How about things that are like, you know, normal, you know, wooden,
you know, vessels or, you know, or whatever metal vessels? So אמר
ליה גזירה הני אטו הני. amar lei gezeirah hani atu hani. Alright,
this will lead to that. So we made everything forbidden.
Actually, what about clothes? What about? Right.
Yeah, so that's the ironic thing. But but so let's take a
look. איתיביה כל הני תיובתא. eitiveih kol hani tiyuvta. So once you
had to say A lead to B, you basically are saying גזירה
לגזירה. gezeirah legezeirah. And once you're saying גזירה לגזירה, gezeirah legezeirah, then
the question is so how do we allow all these exceptions? All
the cases we just got through asking. ושיני ליה כי דשנינן. v’shani
lei ki d’shaninan. And he gave all the same answers we just
gave. Okay, even if we're saying גזירה לגזירה, gezeirah legezeirah, this case
isn't considered an act of טבילה tevilah in a formalistic way. This
case is a לא שכיח lo shechiach case, and we gave all
the answers we just gave. רב ביבי אמר גזירה שמא ישהה. Rav
Bibi amar gezeirah shema yisheheh. We're afraid,
this is sort of like why you can't do certain things on
חול המועד, Chol HaMoed, that if we let you do it on
שבת Shabbos and יום טוב, Yom Tov, then you'll or particularly on
יום טוב, Yom Tov, whatever, but anyway you'll wait till שבת Shabbos
or יום טוב Yom Tov when you've got a lot of time
on your hands and therefore it's a גזירה, gezeirah, we don't want,
we want you to take care of it from beforehand. Okay, which
is particularly true by יום טוב Yom Tov because you know,
because you'll want to be טהור tahor on the יום טוב Yom
Tov and you'll say to your like, you'll anyway you'll leave it
all till יום טוב Yom Tov to take care of it. So
the גמרא Gemara says now that's better because at A that works
for שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov combined, number one. And
number two, it helps explain the difference between whether it became טמא
tamei from לפני שבת lifnei Shabbos or on שבת, Shabbos, or לפני
יום טוב lifnei Yom Tov or on יום טוב, Yom Tov, because
the whole concern is you should have done it beforehand and we
wanted to ensure that you would do it beforehand. So that answer
has fewer גזירה לגזירה gezeirah legezeirah problems, more directly addresses some of
the issues that we've seen. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says תניא
כוותיה דרב ביבי. tanya kevatei de-Rav Bibi. We taught like רב ביבי.
Rav Bibi. כלי שנטמא מערב יום טוב אין מטבילין אותו ביום טוב
גזירה שמא ישהה. keli she-nitma me-erev Yom Tov ein matbilin oto be-Yom
Tov gezeirah shema yisheheh.
The ברייתא braita explicitly says that the reason it's forbidden if it
became טמא tamei beforehand is because we don't want you to intentionally
leave it over for יום טוב. Yom Tov. So this is a
nice explanation. It applies to שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov
equally, also explains the difference for whether it became טמא tamei beforehand
or during. רבא אמר. Rava amar. רבא Rava says, and the this
answer of רבא Rava becomes the basic answer that all the ראשונים
Rishonim adopt, because it addresses most of the concerns from before. מפני
שנראה כמתקן כלי. mipnei shenireh k’metaken keli.
Because it looks like you're fixing something, you know? And you're switching
it from a status of טמא tamei to טהור, tahor, it's also
sort of becoming unusable to usable—I mean, not necessarily unusable, but in
certain areas it is. So that's like you're fixing it, that's like
you're making the vessel. Therefore it equally applies, yeah, like a rabbinic
type of מכה בפטיש. makeh b'patish. So it equally applies to שבת
Shabbos and יום טוב. Yom Tov. You know,
all of these things about the גזירה, gezeirah, all the questions about
how can you draw the water with the vessel, how can the
woman go into the מקוה mikvah with her clothes on, those are
easier to answer. Because it's not נראה כמתקן. nireh k’metaken. The נראה
כמתקן nireh k’metaken has more to do with how, you know, sort
of what it looks like, sort of you know what the act
seems to be about. So in those cases the act is not
about the you know the vessel, the clothes, it's about the woman
going into the מקוה. mikvah. It's not about the bucket, it's about
drawing the water. Okay, so we're going to get to that. So
why is the person basically allowed? Anyway this answer applies equally to
שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov and it deals with some
of the problems, not all the problems, like according to this why
should it be a difference whether it became טמא tamei לפני יום
טוב lifnei Yom Tov or on יום טוב, Yom Tov, לפני שבת
lifnei Shabbos or on שבת? Shabbos? Okay, but at least this answer
deals with a good number of the problems that we raised before.
So the גמרא Gemara says אי הכי אדם נמי, ee hachi adam
nami,
why is a person allowed to go to the מקוה? mikvah? issue
from beforehand because at least in some of the cases, like concern
of קרי keri doesn't apply, concern of סחיטה schita doesn't apply unless
you start worrying about the hair. Anyway, so here, but according to
you, why is a person different? So the גמרא Gemara says, אדם
נראה כמיקר. adam nireh kemeiker. If a person is going to the
מקווה, mikvah, it looks like you're just cooling yourself off. It's not
as obvious that you're going to fix yourself. What? Isn't that a
whole problem in cold water? Well, not in cold water. On שבת
Shabbos you
can—now אשכנזים Ashkenazim don't immerse in cold water on שבת, Shabbos, but
in the גמרא Gemara it was fine. So the גמרא Gemara says,
הני מילי מים יפים. hani mili mayim yafim. That's fine if it's
clean water. מים רעים מאי איכא למימר? mayim ra'im mai ika lemeimar?
If the מקווה mikvah water is dirty, it's obviously you're going just
for מקווה mikvah purposes, not to cool yourself off, so it should
be a problem.
Wait, isn't it the same thing, cooling yourself off and cleaning yourself
off?
Well, that's what the גמרא Gemara is going to say. אמר רב
נחמן בר יצחק, amar Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, פעמים שאדם בא בשרב.
pe'amim she'adam ba besharav. Sometimes a person is coming in the heat,
ורוחץ אפילו במי משרה, verocheitz afilu bemei mishrah, and he is willing
to bathe himself even in like water that was used for soaking
flax, even in disgusting water. He just wants cold water on him.
He doesn't care if it's dirty. So the גמרא Gemara says fine,
תינח בימות החמה. teinach biyemot hachamah.
That's fine if you're going to the מקווה mikvah in the summer.
בימות הגשמים מאי איכא למימר? biyemot hageshamim mai ika lemeimar? If you're
going in the winter, what other reason could you have to be
going into a dirty מקווה? mikvah? אמר רב נחמן בר יצחק, amar
Rav Nachman bar Yitzchak, פעמים שאדם בא מן השדה ומלוכלך בטיט ובצואה.
pe'amim she'adam ba min hasadeh umuluchlach betit ubetzoah.
Sometimes you're coming out from the field and you're covered with טיט,
tit, mud, and צואה, tzoah, excrement, ורוחץ אפילו בימות הגשמים. verocheitz afilu
biyemot hageshamim. And you'll bathe even in cold water, even in dirty
water, but it's not as dirty as the stuff that's on you.
So you'll be willing to go to the מקווה mikvah anyway just
to get the stuff off you even if it's מקווה mikvah water,
even if it's not so clean water. So the גמרא Gemara says
okay, תינח
בשבת. teinach beShabbos. ביום הכיפורים מאי איכא למימר? beYom HaKippurim mai ika
lemeimar? So I get why you're not going to go to the
מקווה mikvah on שבת Shabbos and יום טוב Yom Tov because it
looks like you're just cooling yourself off or you're just bathing. But
how about יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? יום כיפור Yom Kippur you can't
say it looks like you're bathing. You're not allowed to bathe on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. So the גמרא Gemara says, אמר רבא, amar
Rava, מי איכא מידי דבשבת שרי וביום הכיפורים אסור? mi ika midi
debeShabbos shari uveYom HaKippurim assur? Is there anything that's permissible on שבת,
Shabbos, like here going to the מקווה, mikvah, that should be forbidden
on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? So the answer is, I can think
of a couple of things that are permitted on שבת Shabbos and
forbidden on יום כיפור: Yom Kippur: eating, drinking, bathing. So רש"י Rashi
says fine, so רש"י Rashi says no, but things that are connected
to מלאכות, melachos, that should be permitted—do we anywhere have anything מלאכה
melacha related that's permitted on שבת Shabbos and forbidden on יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur? No. אלא הואיל ובשבת שרי ביום הכיפורים נמי שרי. ela
ho'il uveShabbos shari beYom HaKippurim nami shari.
Since we did not forbid a person going to the מקווה mikvah
on שבת Shabbos because it's not as obvious as fixing and מתקן,
metaken, we allowed it on יום כיפור Yom Kippur as well, even
though on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
it's more obvious that you're only doing it for the sake of
the מקווה. mikvah. So the גמרא Gemara says, ומי אית ליה לרבא
הואיל? umi ait lei leRava ho'il? Does רבא Rava hold of this
principle of הואיל, ho'il, since? Since it's going to be allowed in
this case, we'll have to allow it in another case? והתנן, vehatnan,
we taught in the משנה, Mishnah, החושש בשיניו, hachocheish beshinav,
if you have a toothache, לא יגמע בהן את החומץ, lo yigma
bahen et hachometz, you cannot swallow vinegar so that it should go
over your gums and help your toothache, אבל מטבל הוא כדרכו, aval
metabel hu kedarko,
but you can dip your bread in vinegar, which is a more
normal thing, and then eat the dipped bread. ואם נתרפא נתרפא, ve'im
nitrapei nitrapei, if it helps your teeth on the way down then
that's fine. Okay, so that's but you can't directly drink the vinegar,
that's more obvious that it's being done for the sake of רפואה.
refuah. And you can't do רפואה refuah on שבת. Shabbos. ורמינהו, uraminhu,
and then we asked on it, לא יגמע ופלט. lo yigma ufalat.
Another ברייתא braisa is don't swallow vinegar and gargle with it and
spit it out because then it's clearly done לרפואה. lirefuah. אבל מגמע
ובולע. aval megama uvoleia.
You can drink vinegar and swallow it. So here it says you
can swallow the vinegar for the sake of dealing with your toothache,
and the משנה Mishnah says you can't. How do we deal with
that contradiction? ואמר אביי, ve'amar Abaye, כי תנן נמי מתניתין מגמע ופלט.
ki tnan nami matnitin megama ufalat.
When the משנה Mishnah says don't take vinegar on שבת, Shabbos, it
means don't take it and spit it out. Okay, but yeah, you
can take it and swallow it, that's fine. All right, תנא. tnah.
That's the case of the משנה. Mishnah. רבא אמר, veRava amar, רבא
Rava says, אפילו תימא מגמע ובולע. afilu teima megama uvoleia.
Even if we're talking about swallowing, the משנה Mishnah is still forbidding
swallowing. So the משנה Mishnah forbids swallowing, the ברייתא braisa allows it.
How do you deal with that contradiction? ולא קשיא, velo kashya, כאן
קודם טיבול כאן לאחר טיבול. kan kodem tibul kan le'achar tibul.
The question is what time, when, where in the meal are you?
If you're before the dipping part of the meal, אנו מטבילין שתי
פעמים. anu matbilin shtei pe'amim. By the way, in that context,
that whole question why are we מטבילין שתי פעמים matbilin shtei pe'amim
was added after the גמרא, Gemara, and it was added not just
to deal with the fact that we took out the question about
the roasted meat, but it was added in the time of the
ראשונים Rishonim when the normal thing was to not recline during meals.
So the very presence of reclining at a meal was seen as
bizarre. In the time that the משנה Mishnah was being written, reclining
was what you did at any formal meal, even in context in
ברכות Brachos where it's not talking
about פסח Pesach or whatever it
was. You did the reclining because that's part of what makes this
a formal meal, but it wasn't an unusual thing. So anyway, why
did I get onto that? Oh, because of talking about מטבילין. matbilin.
Oh, my מטבילין matbilin led me to the... oh, I made a
גזרה שוה gezeirah shavah מטבילין שתי פעמים matbilin shtei pa'amim to מסובין.
mesubin. Forget that, my head's too much in the סדר. Seder. Okay.
Anyway, so they also would standardly do dippings though, I should say.
The question about מטבילין שתי פעמים matbilin shtei pa'amim is the question
of the first טיבול tivul everybody would do, right, initially. The question
is why you do the second dipping during the actual meal, because
the dippings were more for the appetizer course. So the question about
מטבילין שתי פעמים matbilin shtei pa'amim was the question about the second
טיבול tivul you did for the מרור maror during the meal itself.
Anyway, they would standardly do dippings. So the point is, when are
you swallowing this vinegar straight without dunking the bread? If you're swallowing
it before the dip or, you know, you're finished with the dipping
service, okay, so you still have all the sauces in front of
you, you want to eat the sauce directly, not so bizarre, that
we'll allow. But after you're done with all of the dipping and
all of the sauces, and now you're later in the meal and
you want to go back and have some of the vinegar straight,
that's clearly bizarre, that's clearly done for the sake of רפואה. refuah.
So רבא Rava makes the distinction: when are you allowed to do
it with swallowing it? Before you, you know, while you're still in
the process of the dipping. After the dipping is behind you, then
you can't swallow it, that's clearly רפואה. refuah. One, let's read again.
So רבא Rava says אפילו תימא
דגבי בלע. afilu teiman d'gavei balu. לא קשיא. lo kashya. כאן קודם
טיבול. kan kodem tivul. כאן לאחר טיבול. kan l'achar tivul. Before the
dipping, or I guess before and during, you can have the straight
vinegar. Once you're done with all the dipping and all the sauces
and you've had your fill of sauces, at that stage to be
having the straight vinegar would be a problem. So that's how he
deals with the contradiction. The גמרא Gemara says ואי איתא, v'isa, but
if רבא Rava just says, oh, something's got to be מותר muttar
on שבת Shabbos we have to make it מותר muttar on יום
כפור, Yom Kippur, so how do you make a distinction before and
after the dipping? Like how on the same day can the same
act be forbidden before the meal and permissible... you know, permissible before
the meal and forbidden after the meal? Right? I mean, if it's
going to be... if you say it's permissible on שבת Shabbos it's
got to be permissible on יום כפור, Yom Kippur, so you should
more say, if it's permissible for the first part of שבת Shabbos
it's got to be permissible for the second part. ואי איתא v'isa
for רבא Rava holds of this idea of הואיל, ho'il, נימא, neima,
why don't we say הא וקודם טיבול שרי, ho u-v'kodem tivul sharei,
if you're going to make it permissible to swallow the vinegar before
the dipping, ולאחר טיבול נמי שרי u'v'achar tivul nami sharei you have
to make it permissible after too. Is there any thing that's permissible
for half a שבת Shabbos and forbidden for the other half? So
the גמרא Gemara says, so how did that work? The גמרא Gemara
says you're right, הדר ביה רבא מהא. hadar bei Rava me'hai. רבא
Rava reversed himself from that whole explanation by the swallowing of vinegar
before and after the dipping. And in the end he accepts אביי
Abaye's explanation that if you swallow it it's okay, and the only
case of the משנה Mishnah where it's no good is if you
spit it out. The גמרא Gemara says וממאי דמהא הדר ביה דלמא
מהא הדר ביה, u-mimai d'me'hai hadar bei d'dilma me'hai hadar bei, how
do you know he reversed himself from the vinegar case? Maybe he
reversed himself from his whole position about, you know, about dunking in
the מקוה mikvah and maybe he would have to come to the
conclusion that you can't dunk on יום כפור Yom Kippur because it's
obvious that it's not just cooling yourself off and not just bathing.
The גמרא Gemara says לא לא סלקא דעתך, lo lo salka da'atach,
it doesn't make sense that he reversed himself from his whole approach
that, you know, dunking is... looks like bathing and that we're going
to allow יום כפור Yom Kippur as well. Because to reverse himself
would mean forbidding יום כפור. Yom Kippur. ותניא, v'tanya, we teach in
a ברייתא, Baraisa, כל חייבי טבילות טובלין כדרכן בין בתשעה באב בין
ביום הכפורים, kol chayavei tevilos tovilin k'darkan bein b'tisha b'av bein b'yom
hakippurim,
that anybody who needs to go to the מקוה, mikvah, you can
go to the מקוה mikvah even on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and
יום כפור, Yom Kippur, which is where our question began with, which
is going to the מקוה mikvah on יום כפור. Yom Kippur. So
clearly he has to accept that, and since he accepts that, he's
not going to go back down from his answer that if we
allow it on שבת Shabbos we allow it on יום כפור. Yom
Kippur. So he has to stick by that answer and he has
to therefore drop his whole answer by the vinegar because he has
to be consistent. He says, once we're allowing it, if we allow
on שבת Shabbos we allow on יום כפור, Yom Kippur, certainly if
we allow for part of שבת Shabbos we're going to allow for
the rest of שבת. Shabbos.
Yes, it's part of the logic in the entire סוגיא. Sugya. There's
an assumed גזרה gezeirah here behind the drinking of the vinegar because
you see...
yeah, רפואה. refuah.
No, but רפואה refuah has to do with grinding something to actually
make the treatment, but this is a liquid.
Okay, so two things. First of all, the idea that the... that
the issue is גזרה gezeirah that you'll come to grind... גזרה שמא
ישחוק gezeirah shema yishchok is not in the משנה. Mishnah. It's in
the בבלי. Bavli. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi does not seem like it holds
of that, which is in general true, like things we're talking about
right now, I should say, which is you notice how all of
the answers until רבא Rava were גזרה: gezeirah: גזרה שמא יוציא, gezeirah
shema yotzi, גזרה שמא ישחוק, gezeirah shema yishchok, גזרה שמא יסחוט. gezeirah
shema yisrot. Those are classic בבלי Bavli explanations. The ירושלמי Yerushalmi often
does not have things based on גזרה, gezeirah, but things more being
intrinsically... doesn't mean it doesn't believe there are such... there are גזרות.
gezeiros. But, but,
but more is focus on things being intrinsically problematic, which is closer
to רבא Rava's point: it looks problematic. Putting something in the מקוה
mikvah is נראה כמתקן. ner'eh k'misakein. So by the way, I just
mentioned it because it connected, but the whole thing about taking medicine
on שבת, Shabbos, רפואה refuah on שבת, Shabbos, it seems like that
was just seen as intrinsically problematic. The בבלי Bavli translated it like
a type of professional work on שבת, Shabbos, maybe also a נראה
כמתקן, nira k'metakein, but the בבלי Bavli translated it as a גזרה
gezeirah that you'll come to grind spices to grind the medicine. That
being said, it's not true that they only forbade cases which involved
grinding. They did involve anything that is labeled as רפואה, refuah, certainly
something that's involved with taking some type of a liquid or sap
or solid or whatever, however that thing was made. The interesting question
is, what about doing things like exercise for the sake of רפואה?
refuah? Is that considered רפואה refuah or a massage that you need
to massage a muscle or something? Is something that doesn't involve any
taking of any liquid or solid, that might be out of the
category. But it is true that what's אסור assur for רפואה refuah
is even taking things that are normal foods if they're done דרך
רפואה. derech refuah.
According to the way the בבלי Bavli explains it, it's a concern
גזרה שמא. gezeirah shema. That's not necessarily the way the ירושלמי Yerushalmi
thinks, but I should say that by attributing it to גזרה שמא,
gezeirah shema, it leads to leniencies. For example, it could be according
to some there's no איסור issur taking medicine on יום טוב Yom
Tov because you're allowed to grind on יום טוב, Yom Tov, as
we learned before you can grind spices on יום טוב. Yom Tov.
So there's fundamentally no איסור issur of taking it. Others want to
argue that the whole גזרה gezeirah is more lenient nowadays since we
don't grind our own medicine. So the way the בבלי Bavli frames
it, that's the concern.
Basically רבא- Rava's what was it for יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Because
you don't have a thing of
מעכב? me'akeiv? So therefore אי הכי נמי? ein hachi nami?
Yeah,
what's we allowed for שבת Shabbos we allowed for יום כיפור?
Yom Kippur? But we don't allow a woman to טובל tovil on
יום כיפור. Yom Kippur.
So, okay, so I was going to get there. So, what's the
conclusion of the גמרא? Gemara? The conclusion is we have multiple explanations
for why this is a problem. The first three all have to
do with גזרות, gezeiras, it'll lead to something else, which led the
גמרא Gemara to say, but big, once you're making גזרות, gezeiras, it's
not all logic, גזרה לגזרה? gezeirah l'gezeirah? Once you say גזרה לגזרה
gezeirah l'gezeirah you have to explain the exceptions. And the basic exceptions
were explained falling into two categories: one a type of a לא
שכיח lo shchiach and the other in a formalistic way that's outside
the category. The final explanation, which is the one that the ראשונים
Rishonim really much more prefer, is רבא, Rava, which is it's intrinsically
problematic, it's נראה כמתקן. nira k'metakein. That has the benefit of explaining
that it's not a גזרה, gezeirah, explains it's an equal problem on
שבת Shabbos and יום טוב, Yom Tov, why certain things are not
נראה כמתקן, nira k'metakein, like the idea of drawing water with the
bucket. It appears in an experiential way to a different type of
an act, or even the difference, for example, about a דלות הטומאה
dalut hatumah as opposed to a ראשון לטומאה. rishon l'tumah. If it's
not so much טמא, tamei, it's not so much נראה כמתקן. nira
k'metakein. It does not really sufficiently answer this difference between ערב יום
טוב erev Yom Tov and עד יום טוב. ad Yom Tov. That's
just, okay, we'll go easy on you, it didn't happen before, we'll
make life easy and you didn't have a choice. But that's not
so well explained. But other things fit better in terms of this
נראה כמתקן. nira k'metakein. The one thing that stands out is why
is a person okay? Isn't that נראה כמתקן? nira k'metakein? And תוספות
Tosfos says no, for a person it looks like a different type
of a thing, it looks like bathing. Now the last thing that
we're left with, which is this issue about יום כיפור, Yom Kippur,
that you're allowed to go a type of a לא פלוג לקולא
lo plug l'kulah from שבת, Shabbos, but why are you allowed to
go on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Forget the issue that normally you
can't go to the מקווה. mikvah. Who cares? Why should we allow
it? Aren't you bathing on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Now the basic
point is even on יום כיפור Yom Kippur that we אסור assur
everything, it tends to be that we אסור assur all types of
bathing when
it's
דרך תענוג, derech ta'anug, not when it's, for example, like washing to
remove dirt from you is not considered the prohibition of washing. So
similarly, going to the מקווה mikvah for the fundamental purpose of טבילה
tvilah and not for the fundamental purpose of bathing is not actually
a problem on יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. But it's a little borderline.
And that leads תוספות Tosfos into the discussion of do you need,
is what partly allows you to go on יום כיפור Yom Kippur
and תשעה באב Tisha B'Av the principle of טבילה בזמנה מצווה? tvila
b'zmana mitzvah? That if this is the day that you're obligated to
go, there's a particular מצווה mitzvah that says you should go today
and that overrides whatever type of
תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and יום כיפור Yom Kippur concerns there are.
Even though formalistically it's not technically the forbidden type of bathing, it's
obviously right there at the edge. So תוספות Tosfos says well, it's
a little different, but okay, because it's not like the same דאורייתא
d'oraisa type of idea. But yeah, but somehow it should be done
today. So תוספות'ס Tosfos's answer, he tries, he proves from various גמרות,
Gemaras, so first of all that would have a נפקא מינה nafkamina
for today, because today women don't when they go to the מקווה,
mikvah, it's not exactly בזמנה b'zmana because we have the whole thing
about seven clean days and חומרא דרבי זירא. chumra d'Rabbi Zeira. It's
not the exact time in the תורה Torah they should be going
to the מקווה. mikvah. But תוספות Tosfos says, he proves from another
סוגיא sugya that you don't need the principle of טבילה בזמנה מצווה.
tvila b'zmana mitzvah. Just going to the מקווה, mikvah, even if it's
not בזמנה, b'zmana, which is fundamentally an act of becoming טהור tahor
and not an act of bathing is actually okay even without the
principle of טבילה בזמנה. tvila b'zmana. So then he says so why
don't we then go to the מקווה mikvah on תשעה באב Tisha
B'Av on יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? So if you take a look
at his answer, this תוספות Tosfos כל חייבי טבילות, kol chayavei tvilos,
we'll read a line or two, he says like
this: ומיהו. u'mihu. בתשעה באב
אין טובלין. b'Tisha B'Av ein tovlin. And even though in principle you
don't need טבילה בזמנה tevilah b'zmanah and you can go, we don't
do it on תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. רבי חנניה בן עטיגנוס, Rebbi
Chananya ben Antignos, דאמר, d'amar, כדי הוא בית אלוהינו לאבד טבילה אחת
בשנה. kedai hu beis eloheinu l'abeid tevilah achas b'shanah. Our God, the
mourning for the house of God is important enough that we should
forgo, the very first wide line of תוספות, Tosafos, that we should
forgo one טבילה tevilah of the year. So technically you're allowed, but
it's important as a point of making a point of principle that
you're not going to do it on that day because of the
sense of אבילות. aveilus. Okay, that's תשעה באב. Tisha B'Av. וקאמר בירושלמי
הורה רבי לוי כרבי חנניה בן חנינא בן עטיגנוס. v'ka'amar b'Yerushalmi hora
Rebbi Levi k'Rebbi Chananya ben Chanina ben Antignos. דא דא דא. da
da da. ועוד אומר רי, v'od omer Ri, I'm now four lines
down in the wide lines, שבזמן הזה אין טובלין לא ביום הכיפורים
ולא בתשעה באב. shebazman hazeh ein tovlin lo b'Yom HaKippurim v'lo b'Tisha
B'Av. דדווקא הם שהיו עסוקים בטהרות היו צריך לטבול מיד כדי שלא
יטמאו הטהרות. d'davka heim shehayu asukim b'taharos hayu tzarich litbol miyad kedei
shelo yitmu hataharos. Why would a person go to the מקוה? mikvah?
Because there's a real need, you don't want to stick around being
טמא, tamei, there's real consequences to that. So it might not be
טבילה בזמנה, tevilah b'zmanah, but there are profound, there are important consequences
of not going to the מקוה. mikvah. אבל
השתא דטבילה אינה באה אלא לטהרה לבעלה. aval hashta d'tevilah einah ba'ah
ela l'tahara l'ba'alah. The only real consequence of not going to the
מקוה mikvah is for a woman who's a נדה niddah and that
she's forbidden to her husband. So guess what? יכולה היא לרחוץ ערב
יום הכיפורים כדי שתפסוק שערה וחופפת מעט למוצאי יום הכיפורים, yecholah hi
l'irchotz erev Yom Kippurim kedei shetifsok se'arah v'chofefes m'at l'motzai Yom Kippurim,
so she can arrange it that she'd go immediately מוצאי יום כיפור,
motzai Yom Kippur, משום דצריך חפיפה סמוך לטבילה, mishum d'tzarich chafifah samuch
l'tevilah, וכן בתשעה באב. v'chein b'Tisha B'Av. But she can't go on
the day, דאפילו תטבול ביום הכיפורים ובתשעה באב אסורה לבעלה. d'afilu titbol
b'Yom HaKippurim u'b'Tisha B'Av asurah l'ba'alah. But she can't go on the
day
of תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and יום כיפור Yom Kippur because there
is you're not allowed sex on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av and יום
כיפור. Yom Kippur. So then you were allowed to go because there
was an immediate need and immediate benefit of just being טהור tahor
in general. But now where the whole relevance is to allow sex,
that's there's no thing that would allow to be done on תשעה
באב Tisha B'Av and יום כיפור. Yom Kippur. Which raises interesting questions
about let's say a woman
is attending to her husband and so on like he's sick or
whatever and you need to go to the מקוה mikvah not to
allow sex but to allow touch. Would you be allowed to do
that on תשעה באב Tisha B'Av or יום כיפור? Yom Kippur? Okay
anyway so that's the end of that סוגיא. sugya. Let's take a
look back at the גמרא. Gemara. והשבין שמשקין את המים בכלי אבן.
v'hashavin shemashkin es hamayim b'kli even. So one of the things that
is allowed is to do השקה hashakah but the vessel has to
be טהור, tahor, it has to be in a stone. If the
vessel was not a stone then the vessel would be טמא tamei
through the water and then you would also be being טובל tovel
the כלי. kli. And again that's different than drawing the water with
the bucket because here you're explicitly going to be מטהר metaher and
therefore it could work for the water because that's seen as a
different category but not for the vessel.
The גמרא Gemara means by השקה hashakah not the technical השקה hashakah
for a מקוה mikvah to be מטהר. metaher.
No but the same idea of connecting the
water, dipping the thing in to get the water into the vessel.
Yeah we are to get the water in the vessel into the
מקוה. mikvah. You have water in a vessel and you're lowering it
into the מקוה mikvah so the waters of the vessel touch the
waters of the מקוה. mikvah. Okay so גמרא Gemara says מאי אבל
לא מטבילין. mai aval lo matbilin. So what does the end of
that phrase? So right what
it says משיקין כלי אבל לא מטבילין. mashikin kli aval lo matbilin.
What does לא מטבילין lo matbilin mean? So I've already described it
now the גמרא Gemara will explain it. אמר שמואל אין מטבילין את
הכלי על גבי מימיו לטהרו ביום טוב. Amar Shmuel ein matbilin es
hakli al gabei meimav l'taharo b'Yom Tov. So you don't use the
excuse of doing השקה hashakah on the water to also be טובל
tovel the כלי kli that the water is in. So you can't
use a טמא tamei כלי kli and be טובל tovel the כלי
kli because then it'll be an act of טבילה tevilah of the
כלי. kli. So גמרא Gemara says מני מתניתין. mani masnisin. Who's our
משנה Mishnah going like? לא רבי ולא רבנן. lo Rebbi v'lo Rabbanan.
Not רבי Rebbi and not the רבנן. Rabbanan. דתניא, d'tanya, we tan
in a ברייתא, Braitisa, אין מטבילין את הכלי על גבי מימיו לטהרו
ואין משיקין את המים בכלי אבן לטהרן דברי רבי. ein matbilin es
hakli al gabei meimav l'taharo v'ein mashikin es hamayim b'kli even l'taharan
divrei Rebbi. רבי Rebbi says not only can you not be טובל
tovel the כלי kli that the water is in, you can't even
do השקה hashakah on the water. You can't do either. וחכמים אומרים
va'chachamim omrim and the חכמים Chachamim say, מטבילין כלי אבן על גבי
מימיו לטהרו, matbilin kli even al gabei meimav l'taharo, you can do
טבילה tevilah on the כלי, kli, ובוודאי, v'vada'i, ומשיקין את המים בכלי
אבן לטהרן. u'mashikin es hamayim b'kli even l'taharan. You can do both
the water and the כלי. kli. So the רבי Rebbi says you
can't do either and the חכמים Chachamim say you can do both.
Nobody is going like our משנה Mishnah which says you can do
the water but not the vessel. מני. mani. Who's our משנה Mishnah
going like? אי רבי קשיא
השקה.
ei
Rebbi
kashya
hashakah.
If it's רבי Rebbi who says you can't do either then the
case of the השקה hashakah is problematic because our משנה Mishnah says
you can do the water. אי רבנן ei Rabbanan if the רבנן
Rabbanan who say you can do both, קשיא הטבלה. kashya hatbalah. So
there's a contradiction in the case of the vessel where the רבנן
Rabbanan say you can do it and our משנה Mishnah says you
can't. So גמרא Gemara says איבעית אימא רבי איבעית אימא רבנן. iba'is
eima Rebbi iba'is eima Rabbanan. I can make it go like either.
This is going to be interesting to see how we do this.
איבעית אימא רישא רבי, iba'is eima reisha Rebbi, רישא דברייתא ביום טוב
וסיפא בשבת. reisha d'Braitisa b'Yom Tov v'seifa b'Shabbos. וכולה מתניתין ביום טוב.
v'chula masnisin b'Yom Tov. So here's how the גמרא Gemara is going
to read the ברייתא. Braitisa. It's going to read the statements of
רבי Rebbi and the רבנן Rabbanan that each half of the sentence
is talking about a different case. So let's read this ברייתא Braitisa
again the way the גמרא Gemara is going to read it. It's
אין מטבילין את הכלי על גבי מימיו לטהרו, ein matbilin es hakli
al gabei meimav l'taharo, you can't be מטביל matbil the כלי, kli,
that's the more problematic... The next sentence, ואין משיקין את המים בכלי
אבן לטהרה *ve-ein mashikin es hamayim bikhli even leta-ara*, you can't even
do the water, that's talking about on שבת *Shabbos*. Okay, so in
the first sentence you can't do the כלי *keli*, which suggests that
the water is okay,
that's יום טוב *Yom Tov*. But the second sentence, that you can't
do the water, that's שבת *Shabbos*. So according to that, רבי *Rebbi*
is saying actually on יום טוב *Yom Tov* you can do the—you
can't do the כלי *keli* but you can do the water, which
is exactly our משנה *Mishnah*. Right? רישא דברייתא ביום טוב *Reisha de-Braitah
be-Yom Tov*, וסיפא בשבת *ve-seifa be-Shabbos*, וכולה מתניתין ביום טוב *ve-chulah matnisin
be-Yom Tov*. And our משנה *Mishnah* that makes the distinction of water
and כלי *keli* is יום טוב *Yom Tov*, and that's how to
read רבי *Rebbi* when he says "don't do the vessel," we're reading
it as implicitly "the water is okay," that's on יום טוב *Yom
Tov*. So on יום טוב *Yom Tov* רבי *Rebbi* holds of the
difference of water and vessel. Or, let's go back now and read
how the חכמים *Chachamim* would read that way. The חכמים אומרים *Chachamim
omrin*, מטבילין כלי על גבי מימיו לטהרו *matbilin keli al gabbei memav
leta-aro*, you can do the vessel. When can you do the vessel?
On יום טוב *Yom Tov*. Then you can do both. ומשיקין את
המים בכלי אבן לטהרן *ve-mashikin es hamayim bikhli even leta-aran*, but the
other statement is no, just the water. Just the water, that's שבת
*Shabbos*. So according to that, the Rabbis hold of the same water-vessel
distinction, except they hold it not just on יום טוב *Yom Tov*—on
יום טוב *Yom Tov* they allow both—they hold of the water-vessel distinction
on שבת *Shabbos*. איבעית אימא רבנן *Iba-is eima Rabbanan*, and therefore it
could be the רבנן *Rabbanan* וכולה מתניתין בשבת *ve-chulah matnisin be-Shabbos*. So
our משנה *Mishnah* that states the water-vessel distinction would be שבת *Shabbos*.
Okay, so that's quite a very creative read. The משנה *Mishnah* seems
to make the distinction across the board. For this רבי *Rebbi* and
רבנן *Rabbanan*, we say that actually רבי *Rebbi* and the רבנן *Rabbanan*
both agree to the distinction. The question is, רבי *Rebbi* only allows
it on יום טוב *Yom Tov*, and the חכמים *Chachamim* make the
distinction on שבת *Shabbos*, and our משנה *Mishnah* would be going like
one or the other.